Finding Aid for Alfred H. Lloyd papers, 1879-1926
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Alfred H. Lloyd papers 1879-1926
Lloyd, Alfred H. (Alfred Henry),1864-1927.
2 linear feet and 1 oversize folder
851697 Aa 2; UAm
Professor of philosophy and dean of the graduate school of University of Michigan. Correspondence, speeches, manuscripts of writings, student notebooks from Phillips Academy, Andover, Massachusetts, philosophy lecture notes, and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. Alfred H. Lloyd (donor no. 2260 ) and came to the library in 1947.
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
Alfred Henry Lloyd was born January 3, 1864 in Montclair, New Jersey. He received both his B.A. and A.M. degrees from Harvard, then went abroad to study philosophy at Göttingen University in Berlin and Heidelberg University before returning to Harvard for his Ph.D. which he received in 1893. Upon his return from Europe in 1891, Lloyd came to the University of Michigan as an instructor in philosophy. He would remain here his entire career, receiving steady promotions and eventually becoming full professor in 1906. In 1915, Lloyd also became dean of the University's graduate school. Following the death of president Marion L. Burton in 1924, Lloyd was named acting president of the University of Michigan, serving for eight months, February to September 1925.
As a philosopher, Lloyd was the author of several monographs, including Philosophy of History, The Will to Doubt, and Leadership and Progress. He died May 11, 1927.
The Alfred Lloyd collection includes correspondence, speeches and writings, lecture notes. Within the correspondence, there are letters from Charles H. Cooley, July 1920, William H. Hobbs, Dec. 1918, James H. Tufts, July 1916 and Feb. 1919, the Ann Arbor Branch of the National Security League, Dec. 1918, John Dewey, Oct. 1917, Bertrand Russell, November 1925 and January 1926, and Robert M. Wenley in the years 1925 to 1927.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Graduate School.; Lloyd, Alfred H. (Alfred Henry), 1864-1927.; Phillips Academy.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Philosophy.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Lloyd, Alfred H. (Alfred Henry), 1864-1927.
Contributors:
Cooley, Charles Horton, 1864-1929.; Dewey, John, 1859-1952.; Hobbs, William Herbert, 1864-1952.; National Security League. Ann Arbor Branch (Mich.); Russell, Bertrand, 1872-1970.; Tufts, James Hayden, 1862-1942.; Wenley, R. M. (Robert Mark), 1861-1929.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Correspondence
  - 1915 (Box 1)
  - 1916 (Box 1)
  - 1917 (Box 1)
  - 1918 (Box 1)
  - 1919 (Box 1)
  - 1920 (Box 1)
  - 1921 (Box 1)
  - 1922-1924 (Box 1)
  - January-August 1925 (Box 1)
  - September-October 1925 (Box 1)
  - November-December 1925 (Box 1)
  - 1926 Undated (Box 1)
  - January 1926 (Box 1)
  - February 1926 (Box 1)
  - March 1926 (Box 1)
  - April 1926 (Box 1)
  - May 1926 (Box 1)
  - June 1926 (Box 1)
  - July-August 1926 (Box 1)
  - September-October 1926 (Box 1)
  - November-December 1926 (Box 1)
  - January-March 1927 (Box 1)
  - April-June 1927 (Box 1)
- Speeches and writings
  - Manuscripts of writings, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Manuscript of "The History of the Humani" (Book I) (Box 1)
  - Manuscript of "The History of the Humani" (Book II) (Box 1)
  - Manuscript of "The History of the Humani" (Book III) (Box 1)
  - Typed draft of "The History of the Humani" (Box 1)
  - Manuscript of article, "facts and values" (Box 1)
  - Commencement addresses (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous speeches and articles, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Synopsis of philbsophy course and examinations (Box 1)
  - Tribute to Alfred H. Lloyd by Arthur L. Cross, DeWitt H. Parker, and Robert M. Wenley (Box 1)
  - Bibliography of vritings (Box 1)
- Other materials
  - Philosophy Department materials, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Candidates for appointment in Philosophy (Box 1)
  - Lecture notes for classes in political philosophy (Box 2)
  - Student notes, Phillips Academy, Andover, Massachusetts (Box 2)
  - Photographs (portraits) (Box 2)
    (see also oversize folder UAm)
Related Material
A number of pamphlets and reprints of articles authored by Lloyd have been bound together and catalogued separately (call no. DA 2 L793 P186). Titles include:
Vol. I
Evolution Evolved: A Philosophical Criticism. (The Monist, January, 1899)
Time as A Datum of History. (The Philosophical Review, January, 1899)
Epistemology and Physical Science. (The Philosophical Review, July, 1898)
The Stages of Knowledge. (The Psychological Review, March, 1897)
A Psychological Interpretation of Certain Doctrines in Formal Logic. (The Psychological Review, July, 1896)
The Thinker's Idea of God. (The Inlander, February, 1899)
The Reaction. (The Inlander, June, 1895)
Vol II.
Evolution and Immortality. (The Monist, April, 1900)
The Organic Theory of Society: Passing of the Contract Theory. (The American Journal of Sociology, March, 1901)
The Contribution of The Theory of Evolution to The Science of Teaching. (New York Teachers' Monographs, undated)